So, this is a story
حسنا، هذه قصة
about how we know what we know.
حول كيف نعرف ما نعرفه.
It's a story about this woman,
إنها قصة حول هذه المرأة،
Natalia Rybczynski.
ناتاليا ريبكزينسكي.
She's a paleobiologist,
فهي عالمة في الحفريات القديمة،
which means she specializes in digging up really old dead stuff.
ما يعني أنها مختصة في نبش الكائنات الميتة القديمة جدا.
(Audio) Natalia Rybczynski: Yeah, I had someone call me "Dr. Dead Things."
(الصوت) ناتاليا ريبكزينسكي: نعم، هناك من يناديني "دكتورة الكائنات الميتة".
Latif Nasser: And I think she's particularly interesting
لطيف ناصر: أعتقد أنها مثيرة للاهتمام بشكل خاص
because of where she digs that stuff up,
بسبب أماكن الحفر للبحث عن هذه الأشياء،
way above the Arctic Circle in the remote Canadian tundra.
باتجاه أعلى الدائرة القطبية الشمالية في التندرا الكندية البعيدة.
Now, one summer day in 2006,
في يوم من صيف عام 2006،
she was at a dig site called the Fyles Leaf Bed,
كانت في موقع حفر يسمى "مرقد الجمل"،
which is less than 10 degrees latitude away from the magnetic north pole.
والذي يقع على أقل من 10 درجات من خط العرض بعيدا عن القطب الشمالي الجذاب.
(Audio) NR: Really, it's not going to sound very exciting,
(صوت) ناتاليا: حقا، لن يبدو الأمر مثيرا جدا،
because it was a day of walking with your backpack and your GPS
لأنك تقضي كامل اليومي مشيا حاملا حقيبة ظهرك ونظام تحديد الموقع
and notebook and just picking up anything that might be a fossil.
ودفتر ملاحظات وتقوم بالتقاط أي شيء قد يبدو أحفورا.
LN: And at some point, she noticed something.
لطيف ناصر: وعند موقع ما، لاحظت شيئا.
(Audio) NR: Rusty, kind of rust-colored,
(الصوت) ناتاليا: شيء صدئ، نوعا ما بلون الصدأ،
about the size of the palm of my hand.
بحجم كف يدي.
It was just lying on the surface.
كانت ملقاة على السطح.
LN: And at first she thought it was just a splinter of wood,
لطيف ناصر: ظنت في البداية أنه مجرد شظية من الخشب،
because that's the sort of thing people had found
لأنه تم العثور على مثل هذه الأشياء
at the Fyles Leaf Bed before -- prehistoric plant parts.
في ذلك المكان من قبل-- أجزاء نباتات من عصور ما قبل التاريخ.
But that night, back at camp ...
ولكن في تلك الليلة، وفي طريق العودة إلى المخيم ...
(Audio) NR: ... I get out the hand lens,
(الصوت) ناتاليا: ... أخرجت عدسة اليد،
I'm looking a little bit more closely and realizing
دققت فيها بعناية وأدركت
it doesn't quite look like this has tree rings.
أنه لا يحمل أثار حلقات الأشجار.
Maybe it's a preservation thing,
ربما شيء تم حفظه بعناية،
but it looks really like ...
ولكن يشبه حقا ...
bone.
العظام.
LN: Huh. So over the next four years,
لطيف ناصر: على مدى السنوات الأربع التالية،
she went to that spot over and over,
ذهبت إلى الموقع مرارا وتكرارا،
and eventually collected 30 fragments of that exact same bone,
وجمعت في نهاية المطاف 30 شظية من نفس العظام،
most of them really tiny.
معظمها صغيرة حقا.
(Audio) NR: It's not a whole lot. It fits in a small Ziploc bag.
(الصوت) ناتاليا: ليست مجموعة كبيرة. إذ يسعها كيس زيبلوك الصغير.
LN: And she tried to piece them together like a jigsaw puzzle.
ناصر لطيف: وحاولت جمعها معا مثل أحجية الصور المقطعة.
But it was challenging.
ولكن الأمر شكل تحديا.
(Audio) NR: It's broken up into so many little tiny pieces,
(الصوت) ناتاليا: كانت محطمة إلى عدة قطع صغيرة الحجم،
I'm trying to use sand and putty, and it's not looking good.
حاولت استخدام الرمل والمعجون، لكن لا يبدو الأمر جيدا.
So finally, we used a 3D surface scanner.
في نهاية المطاف، استخدمنا ماسحا ضوئي ثلاثي الأبعاد.
LN: Ooh! NR: Yeah, right?
لطيف ناصر: أوه! ناتاليا: صحيح؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
LN: It turns out it was way easier to do it virtually.
لطيف ناصر: تبيّن أن القيام بذلك بافتراضيا أسهل طريقة.
(Audio) NR: It's kind of magical when it all fits together.
(الصوت) ناتاليا: إنه نوع من السحر عندما يتناسب معا.
LN: How certain were you that you had it right,
لطيف: كم كنت واثقة من أنك تقومين بذلك كما يجب،
that you had put it together in the right way?
أنك قمت بجمعها بطريقة صحيحة؟
Was there a potential that you'd put it together a different way
هل توجد إمكانية لجمعها معا بطريقة أخرى
and have, like, a parakeet or something?
وتحصل على باراكيت مثلا؟
(Audio) NR: (Laughs) Um, no. No, we got this.
(الصوت) ناتاليا: (ضحك) لا. لا، حصلنا على هذا.
LN: What she had, she discovered, was a tibia, a leg bone,
لطيف ناصر: ما حصلت عليه، اكتشفت، كان قصبة الساق، عظم الساق،
and specifically, one that belonged to a cloven-hoofed mammal,
وتحديدا، تنتمي إلى فصيلة الثدييات ذات الظلف،
so something like a cow or a sheep.
شيء يشبه بقرة أو خروفا.
But it couldn't have been either of those.
لكن لم يكن من الممكن أن يكون واحدا منها.
It was just too big.
كان كبيرا جدا.
(Audio) NR: The size of this thing, it was huge. It's a really big animal.
(الصوت) ناتاليا: كان حجم هذا الشيء، هائلا، كان حيوانا كبير الحجم.
LN: So what animal could it be?
لطيف ناصر: أي حيوان يمكنه أن يكون؟
Having hit a wall, she showed one of the fragments
قامت بتقديم واحدة من الشظايا
to some colleagues of hers in Colorado,
لبعض زملائها في ولاية كولورادو،
and they had an idea.
وكانت لديهم فكرة عنها.
(Audio) NR: We took a saw, and we nicked just the edge of it,
(الصوت) ناتاليا: أخذنا منشارا، وقمنا بإحداث ثغرة فيها،
and there was this really interesting smell that comes from it.
وصدرت منه رائحة مثيرة للاهتمام.
LN: It smelled kind of like singed flesh.
لطيف ناصر: كانت رائحته تشبه اللحم المحروق.
It was a smell that Natalia recognized
وكانت رائحة تعرفها ناتاليا
from cutting up skulls in her gross anatomy lab:
من خلال قصّها للجماجم في مختبر التشريح:
collagen.
الكولاجين.
Collagen is what gives structure to our bones.
الكولاجين هو ما يعطي بنيةً لعظامنا.
And usually, after so many years,
وعادة، بعد سنوات عديدة،
it breaks down.
تنهار.
But in this case, the Arctic had acted like a natural freezer and preserved it.
ولكن في هذه الحالة، كانت المنطقة القطبية الشمالية مثل ثلاجة طبيعية وقامت بحفظه.
Then a year or two later, Natalia was at a conference in Bristol,
ولكن بعد عام أو عامين، كانت ناتاليا موجودة في مؤتمر عُقد في بريستول،
and she saw that a colleague of hers named Mike Buckley
وقابلت زميلا لها يدعى مايك باكلي
was demoing this new process that he called "collagen fingerprinting."
كان يقوم بشرح عملية جديدة أطلق عليها اسم "بصمة الكولاجين".
It turns out that different species have slightly different structures
وتبين أن مختلف الأصناف لديها هياكل من الكولاجين
of collagen,
مختلفة قليلا،
so if you get a collagen profile of an unknown bone,
إذا حصلت على تركيبة كولاجين من عظام غير معروفة،
you can compare it to those of known species,
يمكنك مقارنتها مع الأصناف المعروفة،
and, who knows, maybe you get a match.
ومن يدري، قد تحصل على تطابق.
So she shipped him one of the fragments,
لذالك قامت بإرسال واحدة منها إليه،
FedEx.
فيديكس.
(Audio) NR: Yeah, you want to track it. It's kind of important.
(الصوت) ناتاليا: نعم، تريد تتبع ذلك. الأمر مهم نوعا ما.
(Laughter)
(ضحك).
LN: And he processed it,
لطيف ناصر: قام بمعالجتها،
and compared it to 37 known and modern-day mammal species.
ومقارنتها مع 37 نوعا معروفا في عصرنا من الثديات.
And he found a match.
وحصل على تطابق.
It turns out that the 3.5 million-year-old bone
وتبيّن أن العظم البالغ عمر 3.5 مليون سنة
that Natalia had dug out of the High Arctic
الذي وجدته ناتاليا من المنطقة القطبية الشمالية العليا
belonged to ...
يعود إلى...
a camel.
جمل.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Audio) NR: And I'm thinking, what? That's amazing -- if it's true.
(الصوت) ناتاليا: وتبادر إليّ، ماذا؟ هذا مدهش-- إن كان صحيحا.
LN: So they tested a bunch of the fragments,
لطيف ناصر: قاموا بفحص كل الشظايا،
and they got the same result for each one.
وحصلوا على نفس النتيجة.
However, based on the size of the bone that they found,
مع ذلك، إستنادا إلى حجم العظام التي تم اكتشافها،
it meant that this camel was 30 percent larger than modern-day camels.
يعني هذا أن هذه الجمل أكبر 30 في المئة من الجمال الموجودة في العصر الحديث.
So this camel would have been about nine feet tall,
سيكون طول هذا الجمل حوالي 9 أقدام،
weighed around a ton.
ووزنه نصف طن تقريبا.
(Audience reacts)
(تفاعل الجمهور)
Yeah.
نعم،
Natalia had found a Giant Arctic camel.
وجدت ناتاليا جملا عملاقا من المنطقة القطبية الشمالية.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Now, when you hear the word "camel,"
والآن، عند سماع كلمة "جمل"،
what may come to mind is one of these,
ما قد يتبادر إلى الذهن هو واحد من هؤلاء،
the Bactrian camel of East and Central Asia.
الجمل ذو السَنَامَيْن من الشرق الأوسط وآسيا الوسطى.
But chances are the postcard image you have in your brain
ولكن فرص أن تكون الصورة المرسومة في ذهنك
is one of these, the dromedary,
هي صورة واحد من هؤلاء، الجمل الوحيد السنام،
quintessential desert creature --
مخلوق الصحراء الجوهري--
hangs out in sandy, hot places like the Middle East and the Sahara,
يتسع في الأماكن الرملية الساخنة مثل الشرق الأوسط والصحراء،
has a big old hump on its back
على ظهره حدبة قديمة كبيرة الحجم
for storing water for those long desert treks,
لتخزين الماء للرحلات الصحراوية الطويلة،
has big, broad feet to help it tromp over sand dunes.
لديها قدمين كبيرتين وعريضتين لمساعدتها على تسلق الكثبان الرملية.
So how on earth would one of these guys end up in the High Arctic?
فكيف انتهى المطاف بواحد منها هنا في المنطقة القطبية الشمالية العليا؟
Well, scientists have known for a long time, turns out,
حسنا، لقد عرف العلماء منذ فترة طويلة، كما تبين،
even before Natalia's discovery,
حتى قبل اكتشاف ناتاليا،
that camels are actually originally American.
أن الجمال في الواقع من أصول أمريكية.
(Music: The Star-Spangled Banner)
(موسيقى: النشيد الوطني الأمريكي)
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
They started here.
ظهروا أول مرة هنا.
For nearly 40 of the 45 million years that camels have been around,
لما يقارب 40 من 45 مليون سنة كانت الجمال موجودة في الأرجاء،
you could only find them in North America,
يمكن العثور عليها في أمريكا الشمالية فقط،
around 20 different species, maybe more.
ما يقارب 20 نوعا مختلفا، وربما أكثر.
(Audio) LN: If I put them all in a lineup, would they look different?
(الصوت) ناتاليا: إذا وضعتها في مجموعة، فهل ستبدو مختلفة؟
NR: Yeah, you're going to have different body sizes.
لطيف ناصر: نعم، سيكون لديك أحجام مختلفة.
You'll have some with really long necks,
سيكون لبعضها رقبة طويلة جدا،
so they're actually functionally like giraffes.
حتى أنها في الواقع تبدو مثل زرافة.
LN: Some had snouts, like crocodiles.
لطيف ناصر: لبعضها أنف، مثل التماسيح.
(Audio) NR: The really primitive, early ones would have been really small,
(الصوت) ناتاليا: إن البدائية منها، قد كانت صغيرة الحجم بالفعل،
almost like rabbits.
تقريبا مثل الأرانب.
LN: What? Rabbit-sized camels?
لطيف ناصر: ماذا؟ جمال بحجم أرنب؟
(Audio) NR: The earliest ones.
(الصوت) ناتاليا: القديمة منها.
So those ones you probably would not recognize.
لذلك لن تتمكن من التعرف عليها ربما.
LN: Oh my God, I want a pet rabbit-camel.
لطيف ناصر: يا إلهي، أريد حيوانا أليفا جمل-أرنب.
(Audio) NR: I know, wouldn't that be great?
(الصوت) ناتاليا: أعرف، ألن يكون ذلك رائعا؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
LN: And then about three to seven million years ago,
لطيف ناصر: ومنذ حوالي ثلاثة أو سبعة ملايين سنة،
one branch of camels went down to South America,
اتجهت مجموعة من الجمال نحو أمريكا الجنوبية،
where they became llamas and alpacas,
حيث أصبحت لاما وألبكة،
and another branch crossed over the Bering Land Bridge
وعبرت مجموعة أخرى جسر يابسة بيرنجيا
into Asia and Africa.
باتجاه آسيا وافريقيا.
And then around the end of the last ice age,
ثم قبل نهاية العصر الجليدي الأخير،
North American camels went extinct.
انقرضت الجمال في أمريكا الشمالية.
So, scientists knew all of that already,
عرف العلماء كل ذلك بالفعل،
but it still doesn't fully explain how Natalia found one so far north.
لكن لا يزال يصعب تفسير كيف وجدت ناتاليا واحدا في أقصى الشمال.
Like, this is, temperature-wise, the polar opposite of the Sahara.
درجة الحرارة المنخفضة، القطب نقيض الصحراء.
Now to be fair,
لنكون الآن منصفين،
three and a half million years ago,
منذ ثلاث ملايين سنة ونصف،
it was on average 22 degrees Celsius warmer than it is now.
كانت متوسط درجة الحرارة 22 درجة مئوية، أدفئ مما هو عليه الآن.
So it would have been boreal forest,
لكانت غابات شمالية،
so more like the Yukon or Siberia today.
تشبه أكثر يوكون أو سيبيريا اليوم.
But still, like, they would have six-month-long winters
ولكن مع ذلك، مثل، سيكون طول الشتاء ستة أشهر
where the ponds would freeze over.
حيث تتجمد البرك المائية.
You'd have blizzards.
وقد تضرب عواصف ثلجية.
You'd have 24 hours a day of straight darkness.
ويمتد الليل لمدة 24 ساعة متتالية.
Like, how ... How?
مثل، كيف ذلك... كيف؟
How is it that one of these Saharan superstars
كيف تمكن واحد من نجوم الصحراء
could ever have survived those arctic conditions?
من النجاة والعيش في مثل هذه الظروف القطبية؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Natalia and her colleagues think they have an answer.
اعتقدت ناتاليا وزملائها أنهم يملكون الإجابة.
And it's kind of brilliant.
وهو الأمر رائع نوعا ما.
What if the very features that we imagine make the camel so well-suited
ما إذا كانت الميزات التي نتصورها تجعل الجمل يتكيف
to places like the Sahara,
في أماكن مثل الصحراء،
actually evolved to help it get through the winter?
تطورت في الواقع لمساعدته على مواجهة الشتاء؟
What if those broad feet were meant to tromp not over sand,
ماذا لو كان من المفترض أن لا تطأ أقدامه العريضة الرمال،
but over snow, like a pair of snowshoes?
ولكن الثلج، مثل أحذية للتزلج؟
What if that hump -- which, huge news to me,
ماذا لو كانت تلك الحدبة-- وكان الأمر مفاجأة بالنسبة لي،
does not contain water, it contains fat --
لا تحتوي ماءً، وإنما تحتوي دهونا--
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
was there to help the camel get through that six-month-long winter,
موجودة لمساعدة الجمل على مواجهة اشهر الشتاء الستة.
when food was scarce?
عندما يكون الطعام شحيحا؟
And then, only later, long after it crossed over the land bridge
وعندها، في وقت لاحق، بعد عبورها الجسر بفترة طويلة
did it retrofit those winter features for a hot desert environment?
هل عدّلت ميزات الشتاء لتتأقلم مع البيئة الصحراويّة الحارة؟
Like, for instance, the hump may be helpful to camels in hotter climes
مثلا، قد تكون الحدبة مفيدة للجمال في المناخات الحارة
because having all your fat in one place,
لأن كل الدهون موجودة في مكانٍ واحد،
like a, you know, fat backpack,
مثل، حقيبة ظهرٍ للدهون،
means that you don't have to have that insulation
مما يعني أنه لا تحتاج لكل هذه المادة العازلة
all over the rest of your body.
في بقية أنحاء الجسم.
So it helps heat dissipate easier.
لذلك فإنه يساعد على تبديد الحرارة بشكل أسهل.
It's this crazy idea,
هذه فكرة مجنونة،
that what seems like proof of the camel's quintessential desert nature
يبدو كأنه دليل على أن طبيعة الصحراء المثالية
could actually be proof of its High Arctic past.
يمكن أن تكون دليلا على القطب الشمالي قديما.
Now, I'm not the first person to tell this story.
لست الشخص المناسب لأروي لكم هذه القصة.
Others have told it as a way to marvel at evolutionary biology
وقال آخرون أنها وسيلة لنتعجب من علم الأحياء التطوري
or as a keyhole into the future of climate change.
أو مفتاح مستقبلي لتغير المناخ.
But I love it for a totally different reason.
ولكن أحب ذلك لأسباب مختلفة كليا.
For me, it's a story about us,
بالنسبة لي، تتمحور هذه القصة حولنا،
about how we see the world
حول كيفية رؤيتنا للعالم
and about how that changes.
وحول كيفية تغيّر ذلك.
So I was trained as a historian.
تلقيت تدريبا كمؤرّخٍ.
And I've learned that, actually, a lot of scientists are historians, too.
وعرفت أن، في الواقع، الكثير من العلماء المؤرخون أيضا.
They make sense of the past.
جعلوا من الماضي أمرا منطقيا.
They tell the history of our universe, of our planet, of life on this planet.
تخبرونا تاريخ الكون والكوكب الذي نعيش فيه.
And as a historian,
وكمؤرخ،
you start with an idea in your mind of how the story goes.
تبدأ مع فكرة في عقلك حول كيف تنتهي القصة.
(Audio) NR: We make up stories and we stick with it,
(الصوت) ناتاليا: نقوم باختلاق قصص ونلتزم بها،
like the camel in the desert, right?
مثل الجمل في الصحراء، أليس كذلك؟
That's a great story! It's totally adapted for that.
هذه قصة عظيمة! تتكيف تماما لذلك.
Clearly, it always lived there.
ومن الواضح أنه عاشت هناك للأبد.
LN: But at any moment, you could uncover some tiny bit of evidence.
ناصر: لكن في أي لحظة، يمكن اكتشاف بعض الأدلة.
You could learn some tiny thing
يمكن تعلم بعض الأشياء الصغيرة
that forces you to reframe everything you thought you knew.
تجبرك على إعادة صياغة كل شيء كنت تعتقد أنك تعرف.
Like, in this case, this one scientist finds this one shard
مثل، في هذه الحالة، وجد أحد العلماء قطعة واحدة
of what she thought was wood,
مما اعتقدت أنه الخشب،
and because of that, science has a totally new and totally counterintuitive theory
وبسبب ذلك، أصبح للعلم نظرية جديدة تماما ومنافية كليا
about why this absurd Dr. Seuss-looking creature
لما يبدو هذا المخلوق
looks the way it does.
بالطريقة التي عليها.
And for me, it completely upended the way I think of the camel.
وبالنسبة لي، قلب ذلك كليا الطريقة التي افكر فيها حول الجمل.
It went from being this ridiculously niche creature
تحولت من مخلوق سخيف
suited only to this one specific environment,
مناسبة فقط لبيئة واحدة محددة،
to being this world traveler that just happens to be in the Sahara,
ليكون مسافرا في العالم التي صادف أن كانت موجودة في الصحراء،
and could end up virtually anywhere.
يمكن أن ينتهي به المطاف في أي مكان تقريبا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
This is Azuri.
أقدم لكم "أزوري".
Azuri, hi, how are you doing?
"أزوري"، مرحبا، كيف حالك؟
OK, here, I've got one of these for you here.
حسنا، هنا، حصلت على واحد من هاته لكم.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So Azuri is on a break from her regular gig
يستمتع "أزوري" باستراحة من ازعاجه العادي
at the Radio City Music Hall.
في قاعة الموسيقى لراديو سيتي.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
That's not even a joke.
ليست مجرّد مزحة.
Anyway --
على كل حال--
But really, Azuri is here as a living reminder
ولكن، "أزوري" موجود بيننا كتذكير حيّ
that the story of our world is a dynamic one.
أن قصة عالمنا مفعمة بالحيوية.
It requires our willingness to readjust, to reimagine.
وتتطلب الاستعداد للضبط، وعادة التخيّل.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Right, Azuri?
أليس كذلك، "أزوري"؟
And, really, that we're all just one shard of bone away
وأننا على بعد قطعة صغيرة فقط
from seeing the world anew.
من رؤية العالم بشكل جديد.
Thank you very much.
شكرا جزيلا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)